Good morning. Welcome to Zoom bank. Welcome, Governor.
Colleagues, Karen, Paul, and I understand you've brought some additional members
with you this morning. So I'll hand over to you, Governor, to make a statement on
that.
Thank you. Good morning, Morena, Chair and Committee.
It's good to be back here.
So yesterday, the Monetary Policy Committee agreed by consensus to increase the OCR
by 25 basis points to 2.75%. And as you know, inflation
remains above target, reaching 4.1% in the June quarter because of
higher fuel prices. If we take out the direct effect of fuel prices, inflation was
at 2.9%. Monetary policy cannot offset the direct effects of
higher fuel costs on headline inflation.
But what it can and should do is to prevent this shock from becoming
persistent inflation. So with the OCR at an accommodative level, the
Committee judges that a gradual removal of monetary stimulus is appropriate to
return inflation to target while still supporting growth and employment.
And now we do expect growth to strengthen and broaden over the coming year as
household income is supported by lower inflation, and we expect to see
also better labor market outcomes. Thank you. I'll stop there.
Thank you, Governor. I will start off with an opportunity with-
Thank you. And thank you very much for that summary, and I think that cuts right to
the quick of it, of how persistent this inflation is going to be.
Mm-hmm.
And Governor, the MPC says inflation reached 4.1% largely because of those higher
fuel prices, as you identified. How much of that inflation can higher New Zealand
interest rates
realistically achieve? You say it's not intended to do everything, but in setting
this rise, what was the Bank's expectations?
Yeah. So we do expect to see, and we're seeing some indirect effects from
those higher fuel prices. So there are lots of goods and services that use
oil. We have transport, we have freight, we have fertilizers for food, and we
do expect to see some of those indirect effects coming through over the coming
quarters. And for us, it's really important to ensure that this doesn't become
embedded, so inflation stays up around 4 or even 5% over the medium
term. Because if we have that situation, well, then households' purchasing powers
will be eroded. So bringing inflation back towards 2%, we do
expect this to take about a year.
That will help in terms of households getting the purchasing power back, and that
will help job creation as well, because domestic demand is the weak part of the
economy, and the exporting sector are doing better.
So thank you, and it's useful. What specific evidence did you look at when coming
to this decision that shows that underlying domestic inflation is strong enough to
require those higher borrowing costs if you strip out the fuel
shocks-
Yeah
... essentially?
So there is a range of data that we look at.
Of course, core inflation went up from...
The median across different measures of core inflation was 2.4%.
It's now up at 2.7%, so we've seen that going up.
We do expect that to continue increasing somewhat over the coming months.
We expect to see more of those indirect effects coming through.
And then
now we've seen that inflation expectations have been coming down, but they've been
uncomfortably high for a while, particularly on the shorter end, and we know that
that tends to translate into firms passing on costs.
And we've also looked at producer prices, and they have also been relatively high
and actually going up. So the cost pressures for firms are there.
And what we would like to see is that the firms, to an extent that they can, really
look through those higher cost increases, because expecting that inflation will
come down, because that means that we will not have to tighten so much if
firms try to hold back a little bit. So those are...
I don't know, maybe-
Yeah. Thank you
... Paul or Karen would like to add a bit.
Yeah, that's headline inflation, excluding vehicle fuel
increases.
Which inclusive is at 4.1, excluding that it was at 2.9.
Now, that's uncomfortably high-
Yes
... relative to the midpoint of the target, and that would indicate to you that
there are indirect effects that are translating through, and it is higher than, for
example, we saw in February, so pre the crisis.
And our expectation of where it would be pre the crisis as well.
So there are signs there that it is definitely having some impact.
Cool. Thank you. And I think the report paints
a picture that New Zealanders are feeling. It's a pretty bleak picture.
Mm-hmm.
High unemployment, subdued wage growth-
Yeah
... falling real wages, weak household spending, job insecurity, and a cost of
living that everybody is really feeling.
So I guess the question is, what data, looking forward, what data will the
Committee be looking for to conclude that the inflation shock is proving temporary,
that domestic demand is too weak, and no further OCR rises are going to be
required? What will be the critical data sets?
So first of all, we are saying that we're seeing a recovery, but it's uneven.
Mm-hmm.
So we are seeing some really good signs in the New Zealand economy right now, and
particularly related to export. They've been considerably stronger than expected,
and it's not a good environment out there, and exporters are also hit by higher
fuel prices. So clearly there is competitiveness in the agricultural sector, the
tourism, manufacturing. Not all, we know that, but many firms
are doing rather well.
Mm-hmm.
What we're seeing is that they are not hiring so much yet.
They're more using hours.
Mm-hmm.
We can see that in the data. But what we're looking for now, and we're starting to
see signs from, is that the export-led growth is starting to spread to other parts
of the economy. We see that particularly with business investments.
So I just want to be clear that we see an uneven recovery, and we expect it to
broaden. And then with the OCR, it's really important to understand that we're
not on a preset course.
Mm.
So we're saying that at 275, that in historical comparisons is
still relatively low. So we assess that this is good to bring inflation down, but
it's still supporting growth and jobs.
So
if you look at the forward-looking OCR track, there is a probability of another
rate hike, but we also said that now after having done two OCR increases, we can
probably take some time to assess and see how this has affected the economy and
whether we see stronger or less strong second-round effects from the high fuel
prices.
Can I just answer your question on the data?
Yeah.
We look at all of it, and we wish there was more of it for us to look at as well.
In terms of medium-term inflation pressures and our expectations, as key price
setting behavior is key. As the Governor said, there's nothing we can do about that
near-term inflation pressure from higher oil prices.
But what we can and what we will do is stop that from morphing into generalized
inflation pressure. So those indicators of medium-term inflation pressure are quite
key, and this delicate balance that monetary policy is trying to pull off at the
moment-
Yeah
... between supporting growth and preventing the price shock from becoming
generalized inflation.
Yeah. Just honing in on how most people are See the economy,
it's how they're experiencing it.
It's high unemployment, it's subdued wage growth, it's falling real wages, it's
weak household spending. It's all of those indicators that show that everyday New
Zealanders are still feeling this in terms of those considerations.
And you talked, Governor, quite correctly about this being uneven.
We know from in your report points to Auckland and Wellington-
Yes
... feeling this-
Not the South Island.
No, the South Island's always fine, as you know.
But it's not, but it is uneven. But it's not just geographical, it's across
different demographics, particularly young people as well.
Yeah.
How concerning for you is this uneven pattern, and how do you
see the rate rise impacting on that unevenness?
I can start, and I'd be happy to let my colleagues comment as well.
But the thing that we've seen is, yes, it is uneven, but we expect it to broaden,
and we fully understand that many households are not feeling the effects of the
fact that we are starting to be in a broader recovery yet.
The other thing is that we have discussed to what extent is this what we call
business cycle, and to what extent is this more structural.
So for example, take youth unemployment, that we know is high, we know that's a
concern. We discuss things like, we see this in some other countries as well, is
it possibly because firms are investing more in new technologies, and then it gets
more difficult for younger people to come in to the labor market?
And this is a difficult question. There's a difference between what monetary
policy can do and not do in this space.
But actually, we see quite a few structural changes in the economy right now, and
we find them important. But monetary policy is more effective when it comes to the
business cycle. I'm happy to let Paul-
I'd like a chip in, Governor. So low inflation, which is our primary
mandate and our primary objective, we will support the rebalancing
of the New Zealand economy. It will support that growth in the export sector to
spread across the rest of the economy. And I'll go back to my earlier comments.
It's a delicate balance in the New Zealand economy currently.
There's a lot going on. There's an oil shock working its way through a lopsided
economy. As the Governor said, we've got technology nibbling away at different
parts of the labor market. So it's a very complex picture, and lots of structural
changes happening as well. And just to be very clear, our role is to get inflation
down. That's what we can do with monetary policy.
And it's a blunt tool, but the rest of it is beyond the capability of
monetary policy to address its context.
Just very quickly on that, having
a mandate that allowed you to look at things other than just inflation, for
example, unemployment, would that have altered the decision?
That's a hypothetical. We spend a lot of time-
On the labor market
... Yeah. The labor market is still in there.
It's a matter of the degree to which you want to incorporate it into our decisions
in terms of
the mandate. I do think normally in a demand shock, the effect is the same on
inflation, on the labor market. It's a little clearer for monetary policy, and the
breadth of the mandate doesn't matter so much.
It does become more delicate currently when we've got inflation going up and growth
has been lackluster because of the shock.
So picking our way through that, I think the mandate would, at the margin, have an
effect. I can't say whether or not it would've altered the decision yesterday
because we didn't do the process with a dual mandate in our minds.
The other thing we also need to just remember is that we're
talking about a gradual withdrawal of stimulus.
We are not talking about being in a restrictive environment.
We're talking about stimulus still
existing today, and that is all about supporting the recovery of the economy.
And as Paul said, trying to tread that fine line between ensuring inflation doesn't
get away, which will destroy the purchasing power for all households, and
ensuring that the economy still has sufficient condition available in order to see
that movement beyond the export sector into the broader economy.
Thank you.
That's the balance that we're trying to do.
We're going to go now to Dan Bigwa.
Thank you, Mr. Chair. Thank you to your team and to your fellow MPC members for
being here today. Just continuing on the theme of the report, the special topic
around Iran. So what I took from that, if I can summarize, is that
from the June CPI data, the indirect and direct effects accounted for
two-thirds of the inflationary effect. Can I confirm that with yourselves?
Yes. So this is in the...
We would have to look exactly on the pages here.
It's on page
34-
... of the monetary policy report.
And
CPI was at 4.1%, and we do believe that the direct
effect of higher fuel prices contribute to a large share of
that. Then it's always difficult when we try to say how much of that is the direct
effect, and then there's also some of those indirect effect, and we have to make
some assumptions around them, transport costs, et cetera.
So I'd have to read carefully to ensure if I can exactly confirm your number.
But what I said is that we believe that without the fuel cost, annual CPI inflation
would've been more like 2.9%, which is still well above the midpoint of the target
range.
Yes.
And some of that would include some indirect effects from the fuel prices as well.
Yeah. So certainly page 35, I take it that out of the
1.5% June quarter CPI, that essentially one percentage point of that is accounted
for, which is roughly-
Yeah
... two thirds, so.
Yeah.
So in terms of the decision that was made yesterday, can I confirm the
consensus of all members was to increase? Is that correct?
Yes, that's correct.
Okay. You've come before us in the past saying with this crisis,
there will be a certain view to look through this Iran situation.
Yes.
It's continued a lot longer than particularly anticipated.
If core inflation continues to decrease-
Core inflation's increased
... it decreases
... yeah.
Yeah.
What factors will you consider in terms of continuing to look through it or holding
or potential rate rises in the future?
No, so I think the main thing is that we always look to all factors that affect
inflation, and this is a complex process.
So currently we've been looking at how much is inflation affected by the fuel
prices, how much are indirect effects, and do we also see second round effects,
which is more inflation expectations.
Do we see that the wage formation is not functioning as normal
because of this? And then of course, how is demand in the economy?
Because that will also affect inflation over the medium term.
So, we will be looking at a wide range of factor, not just one or two factors.
What we've seen is, and that's what you're saying is because the conflict is
Continuing. We know that it's still very tense in the Middle East.
That means now that the fuel prices are staying at a high level, not at its peak,
but still at a high level. And we see some risk then that that will cause more
indirect effects than we thought a few months ago.
Wonderful.
In May, it was looking considerably better, but we knew that there were risks at
that time that it could flare up again.
Yeah.
It is right now.
Yes. But then you've been engaging across the country with different stakeholder
groups. Any
views around what's doing well? We hear it's doing well.
What is that good news stories that you can see when you're out there engaging with
different sector groups?
Well, we have been engaging. I have a list somewhere of all the different places
we've been to, and I do think it's remarkable the way that the
business sector is working through this period.
And we're seeing high demand for New Zealand exports.
And I think there are two factors, the fact that they are competitive, again,
cultural sector is competitive, commodity prices are relatively high.
But also that they're being flexible in terms of finding new export markets.
And then there are still some firms that are struggling more, and they're mainly
related to domestic demand.
Mm-hmm.
And that is why we keep on saying, and Karen also just pointed it out, that getting
inflation down will help those small businesses because we know then that
households will start spending more, and that will flow through.
So currently, and we have that in the report,
total disposable income is actually growing more than spending, so households are
saving.
Mm-hmm.
There's a graph on that somewhere in the report.
And it's not strange that households are doing some precautionary saving in this
environment, but that also means that there's an upside.
Mm-hmm.
When they see that the economy starts growing-
Mm-hmm
... they feel less job insecurity.
Mm-hmm.
We do see inwards migration. We see people moving across different parts of New
Zealand to find jobs. That will help this adjustment, and that means that we can
also see the household consumption growth starting more strongly again.
And what's the bank seeing in Auckland?
It has been a particularly hard time in Auckland with elevated employ-
Yeah.
Yeah
... unemployment. But confidence indices seem to be improving.
What is the bank seeing with respect to Auckland?
So that's true. We highlight both in terms of house prices and unemployment.
Unemployment is higher in Auckland than it is in some other parts of the country.
It's probably related somewhat to
youth unemployment.
Mm-hmm.
A lot of students, et cetera, are looking for a job, finding it more challenging in
that environment. It's also probably related to the fact that house prices have
been important for household wealth, and house prices haven't really rebounded in
Auckland yet.
Mm-hmm.
So we're discussing this, and there is an in-depth here talking a bit more about
household consumption. And also, unfortunately there we don't have great data
across the country, but we have some indicators of what is affecting that.
I don't know, maybe Paul you'd like to add.
Oh, I think you've nailed it, actually.
I think Auckland, times are challenging in Auckland.
Unemployment, it's quite unusual to see a difference in unemployment above 6% in
Auckland versus 4% in the South Island.
So there are regional differences are quite extreme at the moment.
Essentially because the South Island and parts of the North Island are more locked
into, I don't know if booming is the right word, but an export sector that is going
very well. Thank goodness, because that's the sort of growth engine in the economy
at the moment. But it's a long way from Invercargill to Auckland for those effects
to make their way through the economy and through the geography.
Just a bit on that topic.
Mm.
The regionalism.
Is there a risk that Auckland, if we take it by itself,
either is in recession or will fall into recession?
I think it's like
interest rates in Auckland, we've got one tool, we've got one currency, we set it
for the whole country. It's a weighted average of economic conditions across
the country. And this is part of the challenge for monetary policy at the moment is
this idea of different parts of the country performing very differently.
But it's growth in Auckland going backwards.
We don't have exact regional data.
Sometimes we get regional data, but it tends to be more lag than GDP data.
Yeah.
So currently we have GDP for the whole country only for the first quarter.
We're still waiting for the second quarter data-
Yeah
... which we expect to look rather weak. But we are in the third quarter already.
We are in the September quarter where we think that things have actually started to
recover. So getting that kind of regional data for the whole economy will take
even longer is my understanding. But that's why we did look at some other measures
like unemployment, like the house prices.
I do think that we will see when we see the broadening of the recovery,
that also some of those areas will start performing better.
And some of the things you look at there are the surveys that are occurring, right?
Yeah.
And are we starting to see a little bit more confidence-
Confidence returning
... returning in business and households?
And certainly from a business perspective, those confidence surveys are showing a
small uptick as well. So you're starting to see, but that's right at the very start
of it. That then needs to translate into activity.
But certainly the surveys that are being done are starting to show more confidence
around forward-looking orders and even past activity from a business perspective.
So yes, while there might still be some divergence, there are some signs that
things are starting to pick up in aggregate a bit more.
But as been pointed out, there are distributional
differences and issues there, and that takes time to change and move.
And there will always be a lag.
And GDP growth was 0.8 in Q1.
Yeah.
Which wasn't too bad in the global context of what's going on.
And yes, a lot of it was coming out of the export sector.
Yes.
But there is growth in this economy.
It just seems that every Q2, this year it's conflict in the Middle East, last year
it was tariffs-
Mm-hmm
... and all the uncertainties associated with that.
But in between, we grow, and we can grow.
And this decision out of the committee yesterday is not standing in the way of
that.
Mm-hmm.
It's supporting growth in the economy and employment.
But it's calibrated to reduce those second-round
inflationary effects through expectations and through pricing behavior of
businesses.
Thank you.
But it's a very delicate balance.
I've been very patient, Mr. Chair, so I'd just like the spot that I was requested a
few minutes ago into my primary one.
Invitation.
So actually, it trembles quite well off of that final point, which is just you've
noted, obviously, commodity prices, I think we're all aware that's part of the
reason that we're seeing this kind of K-shaped differential between North and South
Island. The commodity prices, we're kind of lucky because of its price.
So if high commodity prices weren't being experienced internationally, and
therefore that we wouldn't see that benefit our export markets, what would the
impact be on our economy right now?
Because I guess what I'm trying to get a handle on is the things that we actually
have control over domestically versus those international things.
Yeah. No, but I think that if we look at the commodity prices, New Zealand has been
very negatively affected by the oil price.
Mm-hmm.
And that is also part of that. So first we had in terms of trade, actually
looking worse. And now when we see that oil prices, I will not use the word
stabilized unfortunately, but they're highly volatile still.
Mm.
But we've seen the other commodity prices that are good for New Zealand, dairy,
meat, these kind of things being high.
But we also know that the sector is competitive, fundamentally competitive.
Mm.
So this has just made, if you look at the exporting numbers, they're extremely
strong right now. So I think if we saw a very strong reversal, of course that would
be difficult.
Mm.
But this sector is so competitive that they could take softening of those very
strong commodity prices.
I think the other point there, Chloe
There is an element of good fortune in the fact that commodity prices are high for
the things that we're good at currently.
With export.
But also, the long-term trend in New Zealand's terms of trade-
Mm
... is pretty positive, actually.
So we are quite good at shifting resources into industries and sectors that do end
up getting, where global prices do tend to increase more than import
prices. Now if I may just-
And sorry, can I just say monetary policy does have an influence there through the
exchange rate.
Yes, exactly. Yes.
So we can't ignore that either.
Totally.
Yeah.
Now I just want to explore some of the logic of this decision and then the
implications of it, bearing in mind, as you two in particular well know, I'm very
aware of the blunt instrument that is monetary policy.
So I guess just lay out a few premises for the sake of continuing to explore this.
Firstly, just to be really clear, as you said in your opening statement, 4.1%
inflation is largely being driven by, or it's outside the target band by virtue of
the fossil fuel crisis, Trump's war on Iran. Yes?
Headlines.
Yes.
It's called headlines, yeah. We know that monetary policy cannot reopen the Strait
of Hormuz. It cannot decarbonize our economy and reduce our exposure to imported
fossil fuel inflation. We accept that premise. Cool.
Yes.
So only fiscal policy can do those things.
Fiscal policy can open the Strait of Hormuz.
No, but it could decarbonize our economy.
It could invest in renewable energy and substitutes, either could.
Those are choices of the elected officials.
Thank you very much for making that explicit.
So just to that effect, I just really want to understand, because many people out
there will be saying, out in regular people land, whereby I completely understand
you guys don't have the same platform or the freedom of politicians to unpack this
stuff, so I really would love to give you the opportunity to explain how monetary
policy is a blunt instrument, but you are largely compelled by virtue of your
enabling legislation to act when inflation is outside of the target band, but you
can't actually deal with those structural fundamentals of the economy.
Sure.
We can deal with the indirect effects.
Yes.
And
we've seen that. We had a few years back a similar situation, it was
very different in many ways.
Mm-hmm.
But what happened-
It was all in committee.
Yeah. So what we've seen is that monetary policy is really important in terms of
containing the indirect and second-round effects of things like supply-side
shocks.
Mm-hmm.
And it does matter a lot for inflation expectations, for
how core inflation evolves, and over the medium term, that turns out to be headline
inflation. And what we're seeing right now is that there's a risk that
unless we respond in monetary policy,
those inflation expectations will get out of hand, and we will see a lot of firms
taking the opportunity to hike prices in this environment.
Yes. Right.
And we are seeing both some bad examples, but some also good examples of firms
showing restraint, because then we will get back to inflation at a low and
stable level more quickly, and that would really benefit everyone.
But this will not happen without us doing anything.
No. So just thank you. I really appreciate you outlining that rationale.
So to your point of inflationary expectations and price setting behavior, to make
that really concrete for, again, real people outside of this space who don't
necessarily understand this economic terminology, what you're talking about there
is effectively, for lack of better terms, the animal spirit of the economy, whereby
you have firms that can see that there is inflationary pressure, and they therefore
can respond by setting prices at a certain level, which can arguably be justified,
and consumers will just accept it because there is high inflation.
Is that effectively what we're talking about?
Well, so look, firms are also hurt by higher costs presently.
Totally. Yeah.
So we have to allow for this, and I understand, I think it's really good to try to
explain it in a sense and not use so much of the too complicated economic language,
but some firms are hurting from higher costs.
Mm-hmm.
And they're looking at, how can I survive in this environment?
And their margins are small.
Yes.
Then there are other firms who
fuel costs are not a big part of their cost structure, but they might still use
this as an excuse to hike prices anyways.
Yep.
And for us, the balance is to try to make sure that we don't see the
opportunistic price setting behavior bringing inflation back, because it will be
better for everyone of the medium term.
And we're trying to take a balanced approach, and what we pointed out here is that
we're coming from a relatively low level-
Mm-hmm
... at 2.25, and 2.5, 2.75 is still what we
call accommodative, which is a technical term, but is saying that we think it's a
level that's consistent with still supporting growth and jobs.
100%. Thank you for pointing out those differences and that some may take that
opportunistic approach, because I think that that is a really important thing to
understand, also monetary policy, obviously a blunt instrument.
So we know that a higher OCR has the impact of contracting spending.
It's the correlation there. Which then tends to correlate with higher unemployment.
Yes?
The restrictive OCR-
Well, it depends on where you're coming from
Yeah.
So we're coming from a level where the OCR is below what we think is restrictive,
so we think is actually stimulatory.
So what we're doing now, because the monetary policy transmission, and this is
again, a technical term, it goes through a number of different steps.
Mm-hmm.
So one is having an effect on wholesale interest rates, one is having an effect on
household and firms' expectation, and one is an effect on potentially dampening
demand. Currently, the main effects will be through wholesale interest rates,
exchange rate, and expectations, not so much on dampening demand,
because we're coming from a low level.
Last question.
You've had your 10 minutes.
Okay. So I guess to try and bring this all together, you noted at
page eight of your report that growth and activity may not flow through into
additional employment as expected, particularly if businesses are relatively more
focused on efficiency and technology investment.
To that effect, we are currently going through quite a substantive industrial
revolution, albeit lightly with the likes of AI tools being deployed and otherwise.
So, you guys have very blunt tools at your disposal, typically, by
releasing more expenditure into the economy,
we then see growth and then that tends to, historically at least, result in higher
growth, which then spills over into higher wages, more employment and otherwise.
But this to me seems like quite a stark warning that we might not necessarily see
that recovery occur in that same way.
Can you unpack for us what that actually means for the economy and potentially the
efficacy of the tools at your disposal?
Yeah, so this sentence is related to the record of the meetings, and we were
talking about different kinds of risks.
Mm-hmm.
So of course, there is a large upside potential of firms investing in new
technologies.
Mm-hmm.
Creating productivity gains that tend to increase incomes.
And what we've seen historically is that they tend also to create actually more
jobs.
Mm-hmm.
What we're considering now is what we mentioned before, we're seeing youth
unemployment in particular being high.
Yes.
And there is a discussion here and in other countries, are firms a bit more
reluctant to employing younger people because they might be able to use some tools?
And we don't have a clear answer on this because no one actually can tell you with
certainty.
No.
But we are saying that we're watching this, we're trying to analyze it.
We'll keep an eye on it. We don't think it's going to be an issue over the...
We use the word medium term quite often because it tends to give much better
incomes, so you can hire more people.
But in the near term, we're wondering if it may have an impact, particularly on
younger people.
I think we've used that a short term in the-
We'll ask them that question at the right times.
Sorry?
Thank you.
All right. I'll go to Nancy Lo.
Thank you. I have three short questions.
Firstly, welcome to the external members as well.
I understand that all three of the external members are here.
Yes.
Is there a particular reason or would they like to share something on what they
consider, too?
So we discussed this, and we would be happy to.
We offered a bigger table again, but we think a nice way of doing it is that we can
have the external members come up and answer questions.
Yeah.
And Paul offered to-
I'm very happy
...
to rotate a little bit. So we have Prasanna Gagaik, Hayley Gourley, and Carl Hansen
here. So they're happy to answer questions as well.
Yeah. So then my question to the external members would be when you went into the
meeting-
Did you all go in with your, I guess, your preference to vote for an increase
already, or was that a more in-depth conversation with them?
Yeah. Polly, want to start with that?
We don't want Andrew to answer, but-
Yeah. Thank you for the question.
As you can imagine,
even in between meetings, even though this is not my full-time job, in between
meetings, I try to keep an eye on what's happening in the economy and globally.
And so one does tend to get an inkling and start thinking about things.
But I certainly find that once we get the material from the Reserve Bank, which is
very comprehensive, it really updates you, and at that point,
we go to the first day or two, and we're getting staff presentations.
We get an opportunity to clarify what we're reading, and it's really at the end of
that stage that we start putting quite a bit of thought to what we think
we're going to recommend as individuals.
Okay.
Because the staff material includes the modeling and the forecasting-
Understand
... which we don't get from just reading the general news in media.
That's a good point to understand.
I always find that it's very instructive to get the material from the staff.
Good. Okay.
And it's also very interesting to find out what the other members are
thinking. So we talk about those things in a very structured way.
We all form our own views, and then we go through a structured approach of
what each of us are thinking about, so that we're keeping independence-
Okay
... and not falling into a group think kind of way.
Now, coming back to the governor-
Mm-hmm
... apart from learning in discussions within the inside, obviously, we're also
looking at what the other countries are doing.
And as noted, for example, in Australia, the OCR at the moment is at
4.35%. Looking into the UK, which is another area that we look into, is also quite
high. However, the inflation rates in both these two countries are quite
different.
Mm-hmm.
What is your learning from the other countries?
Because we all go through the oil crisis together.
Yeah, and it's different starting points-
Mm
... and different structures in the economy.
So we do look a lot at what's happening in other countries, both because they are
important as export markets for us, but also because it can have implications,
for example, for the exchange rate.
Yeah.
It tends to be a relative-
Yeah
... feature. So we look at that. We know that, for example, in Australia, their
economy was...
I'm trying to be careful with the words I use.
But they had high growth and low unemployment, so they were sort of hiking already
before-
Yeah
... the oil prices hit and affected them as well.
So they're up at a considerably higher level than we are.
And then it differs, and we need to look at each country is different, and I'm
certain, talking to some of these other governors, that they focus on doing what's
right for their country, and we're focusing on doing what's right for New
Zealanders.
And people are reacting differently, so, and economies, you're right, are
different.
It depends on the energy intensity of an economy as well, and some are net
exporters.
Mm-hmm.
And so that's a very different proposition to the one that we would face here in
New Zealand. And some of them are adopting different fiscal approach to it as well.
Yeah.
So you see subsidies in some economies, but that's a trade-off too.
Yes.
What does that mean from a fiscal deficit perspective as well?
Thank you. Thank you, members. I've just the time, got to keep moving. Dr. David.
Yeah, just a little something, thank you, Nancy-
Sure
... for your question.
With the international comparators, it's quite instructive, isn't it?
I just wondered, we're looking at inflation, OCR, we mentioned the exchange rate as
something. Paul was talking about terms of trade.
Yeah.
All those factors are really-
Factors
... important for us, aren't they?
One I'd chuck in there is the cost of capital and respective comparators.
How do we line up there?
Mm-hmm.
So this is the question that is maybe more for when we're here for financial
stability and these kind of questions, but we look at it from the perspective in
terms of
how well the transmission of monetary policy is functioning.
Mm.
And one of the things that we highlight in a special chapter here is around what we
call financial conditions, is that we've seen that the transmissions onto wholesale
interest rates, mortgage rates, lending to the corporates have been reasonably
normal. But we've seen less of a pass-through to deposit rates.
And we think that they should go up a little bit more.
It's not quite what you're asking, but that's the monetary policy part of it.
Mm-hmm.
So we do discuss financial conditions and how that is affecting households and
firms.
Thank you. Dr. Panch, your turn.
Yeah. Thank you. So in your report, you say inflation is expected to remain
elevated, as you have also mentioned, and you're thinking that it will return to
target band by mid-2027. And you have also mentioned that a big contributor in this
inflation is the fuel prices.
Mm-hmm.
Then how did you come to this number, that it needs to be 25 basis points increase?
You mentioned some assumptions. Can you elaborate on those assumptions so that we
know?
Yeah. So the basic foundation for this is that we're coming from a low
level of the OCR.
Mm-hmm.
So we wanted to move towards what is more an OCR that is
neither accommodative or restrictive, because inflation is high, and we want to
stop this indirect and second-round effects from causing persistent high inflation.
And we thought that what we call a gradual approach-
Mm
... is appropriate, which means that we move gradually, and then we can also assess
and see the effects. But we know that takes some time for monetary policy to have
an effect. So this time we had a discussion, and that's also in the record of the
meeting, saying that if we waited too long, there was a risk that inflation would
get out of hand, and then we would have to tighten much more aggressively later on.
So that's why we thought 25 basis points was weighing these factors, bringing
inflation down by still supporting growth and jobs.
So do you know what kind of impact it will have on domestic?
Because there is a big international factor in there as well, which you can't
control. Right?
Mm. So we think that this will still be a level of the OCR that
supports growth and jobs. I think if we went up to
OCR policy rates where they were a few years back, a 4% or 5%, that would be
clearly restrictive, but this is still a level that we think will support the
recovery in the New Zealand economy while still keeping inflation in
control.
Thank you. We're now approaching the quick-fire round.
Thank you.
Please begin.
So we've got youth unemployment the highest since the GFC.
We've got unemployment the highest since 2000,
171,000 people unemployed, 440,000 people
underutilized in the economy. Unsurprising that we're seeing negative real
wage growth forecasts for the coming year.
So for households, that means a real drop in income.
And Karen, you talked about one of the things that we're seeing across the economy
is those businesses that rely on domestic spending-
Mm
... are struggling more than those that are in the export-led sector.
Mm.
How much of a concern is this incredibly high unemployment and
negative wage forecasts in terms of the ability of those businesses that rely on
domestic spending?
Do you want to start?
Yeah.
Okay.
I'll start, and I think we outline it quite clearly in the record of the meeting
and in the document itself that those conditions that you're talking about are part
of the story, which is dampening the potential risks of higher inflation.
So we have to think about this in the context of inflation.
And so from a medium-term perspective, those aspects are some of the things that we
are thinking about that are dampening that.
It's important, however, that recovery does occur at the same time as inflation
comes down because that is the thing that will restore the purchasing power for
households, and that is where we're focused.
Just a pin to put what you're thinking about is whether we're seeing a twin
structural change in terms of technology and tools-
Yes
... particularly around youth unemployment, could make for a really good briefing
to a future select committee or a special topic to consider because that's quite an
important story.
Yeah.
Yeah, we want to do that.
Just a sub from earlier, which I indicated I was to share then I'd come back to, on
Chloe's questions around the fossil fuel and inflation and in your chapter on
global economy and financial markets On page
27, you talk about European and Asian natural gas prices have
continued to increase, reflecting renewed disruption to gas supply chains.
Mm-hmm.
Of course, that's a flow onto, that's LNG.
Yeah.
So in terms of future decisions by the committee, of course,
whether or not New Zealand has tethered itself to those international rising
markets of increasing and constrained supplies of LNG, is this something you'll
need to take into consideration if a decision is made to go ahead with New Zealand
having a terminal?
Well, as a principle, what we take into our forecast are things that have been
formally decided on. So I just want to point that out.
Mm-hmm.
That we are doing forecast with the information that's available, looking at a wide
range of factors, and when we have a decision that we know will be implemented,
we'll try to incorporate that.
So if a commercial contract was to be signed, the forecast would need to be updated
reflecting differing gas prices.
You know what, we're not in a position to comment on things like that.
I appreciate that.
But what I will say is that in an era where global fossil fuel prices are
high and variable, if New Zealand was less dependent on fossil fuels, then
inflation would be lower.
Thank you.
Claire's got a-
Your monetary policy statement from February 2024 stated the reinstatement of
interest deductions is expected to increase demand for New Zealand companies from
interested investors. You also said we view the reduction in the bright line rule
as putting upside pressure on house prices.
Commentary that followed that, however, stated that we didn't see the corresponding
increase in house prices as a result of detected high unemployment, the number of
New Zealanders that are leaving. Can you confirm that that's an accurate analysis
of your as-assessment of this policy application on house price inflation to date?
Well, house prices, we are discussing
house prices related to household consumption in chapter four too.
I'm being a little bit reluctant to go back and comment on something that we don't
have in front of us, so we can really check that.
We're believing that currently, we are seeing and we're stressing that there's
quite a lot of divergence across different parts of the country.
Again, house prices in South Island have rebounded.
Yeah.
They're increasing currently in most parts, and then there is more subdued house
price growth in particular Wellington and Auckland.
Yeah.
And our expectation is for house prices to start growing from-
Yeah
... the middle of next year.
Yeah. I think the thing you also need to take into account here is-
No, just-
... it's not just a cyclical story that you need to think about.
Have you seen a structural change as a consequence of the work that was done two or
three years ago-
Mm-hmm
... around changing the conditions for supply.
Mm-hmm.
So there are structural as well as cyclical elements you need to take into account.
Thank you. Governor, just a couple of quick questions from me in closing.
Yeah.
I heard you mention earlier that, I don't want to misquote you, but total domestic
spending is growing or something to that effect. Could you just elaborate on that?
Well, so-
Or just give us your-
... total disposable income is growing more than spending.
And we see that households, and as a result of that, household savings has been
going up, and so what we're saying is that overall, and it's actually true, even
if you look at total real disposable incomes, they're actually positive.
So even if many households are hurting right now and real incomes per capita is not
strong, total, because the hours worked has been increasing.
There are actually more people employed.
Just in the June quarter, there was 13,000 more people in employment, so that's
causing total disposable incomes to grow.
Mm.
But households are being cautious.
And what we're saying is that we're seeing that if households have more confidence,
and we actually see consumer confidence going up right now, we could see
consumption growth coming back even quicker than we expect.
Fantastic. And just in terms of that, 30 seconds, what would your message be to New
Zealanders that are potentially unsure about what's happening with the OCR and all
the volatility?
The Reserve Bank is focused on bringing inflation back.
It will make purchasing power come back, and that will also help with jobs and
growth. We're seeing a broadening of growth in the New Zealand economy, and we will
stay very steady and reliable in delivering on our mandate.
Thank you so much for your time, and great to have additional committee members
here this morning to join the discussion. Thank you.
Thank you.
Thank you so much.